Guide to the Anne Baker papers, 1976-2018 RL.11441
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Anne Baker papers
1976-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Baker, Anne, 1951-
RL.11441
4.7 Linear Feet
Anne Baker was an abortion counselor, serving as the Director of Counseling at the Hope Clinic for Women in Granite City, Illinois for the majority of her career. The Anne Baker papers consist of informational pamphlets, handouts, forms, workshop evaluations, personal writings, newspaper clippings, photographs, correspondence, VCRs, DVDs, cassettes, buttons, and sweatshirts.
Arrangement
Files are organized into six different series. These include: Abortion-related workshops and inservices, 1981-1999; Hope Clinic for Women, 1976-2013; Personal, 1978-2014; Publications, 1979-1988; Books, Pamphlets, and Thesis, 1988-2000s; and Audio-Visual, 1985-2010.
Biographical / Historical
Anne Baker received her B.A. in Social Welfare from S.I.U. Edwardsville in 1975. She went on to work at the Planned Parenthood of St. Louis from 1975-1976. Baker received her M.A. in Counseling Psychology from Lindenwood College. In 1995, she published Abortion and Options Counseling: A Comprehensive Reference. Baker worked as a counselor and later the Director of Counseling at the Hope Clinic for Women in Granite City, Illinois from 1976-2012.
The collection also contains significant records of the Hope Clinic in Granite City, Illinois. The Hope Clinic was founded in 1974 with Dr. Hector Zevallos as the medical director. The clinic was bombed and subsequently rebuilt in 1982. Dr. Hector Zevallos and his wife Rosalie Jean Zevallos were kidnapped by an anti-abortion terrorist group called the Army of God. They were released eight days later. The Hope Clinic remains in operation today, although the counseling wing of the clinic was disbanded in 2012 due to budget cuts.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Anne Baker papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2014 and 2018.
Collection Overview
The Anne Baker papers contains documentation of Baker's personal life and of her professional role as the Director of Counseling at the Hope Clinic of Granite City, Illinois. They include materials from workshops and trainings she gave, secondary literature about abortion counseling, correspondence, materials from different protests that she and other Hope Clinic staff attended, personal notes, histories of the Hope Clinic, and newspaper clippings from the kidnapping of Dr. Hector Zevallos and his wife Jean Rosalie Zevallos.
Abortion services -- United States -- History; Abortion counseling -- United States; Women's health services -- Law and legislation -- United States; Hope Clinic for Women; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Baker, Anne, 1951-
- Abortion-related workshops and inservices, 1981-1999; undated
  - Birth Control inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Breaking Up workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Decision-Making Process workshop, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Grieving and Loss inservice, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Fetal Development inservice, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Guilt workshops, 1981-1983; 1985; 1987 (Box 1)
  - Letting Go of Other People's Problems inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Life and Death inservice, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Managing Stress inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Patient Care inservice, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Pregnancy Testing Counseling workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Purpose of Pre-Abortion Counseling inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Burn-Out workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Repeated Abortion workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Second Trimester Expansion from First Trimester clinic inservice, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Stress, Sanity, and Survival inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Post Trauma Debriefing workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Tubals at Hope inservice, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Vasectomy inservice, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Where Do You Work? workshop, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Why Counseling Sometimes Takes Longer workshop, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Repeat Abortion and 2nd Trimester Abortion workshops, 1999 (Box 1)
  - National Abortion Federation Workshop - Emotional Pain: Exploring Counseling Issues, Philadelphia, PA, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Shame/Guilt inservice, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Religious inservice, 1990; undated (Box 1)
- Hope Clinic for Women, 1976-2013
  - Organizational materials, 1980s; 2010; circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - Abortion counseling materials, 2002; undated (Box 1)
  - Abortion - mental health resources: Hope Clinic counselors' readings, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Hope Clinic counselors' meetings and inservices, 1978-1986 (Box 1)
  - Informational resources, 1978; 1980s (Box 1)
  - Resources to address spiritual concerns of abortion patients, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Workshop responses, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Panel on religion/spirituality and abortion materials, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Counselor training resources, 1984; 1990; undated (Box 1)
  - Abortion resources, 1978-2009 (Box 1)
  - Administrative materials, 1978-2011 (Box 1)
  - Workshops, handouts, and evaluations, 1978-2001; undated (Box 1)
  - Women and Alcoholism materials, 1976-1996; undated (Box 1)
  - Workshop training, 1987; undated (Box 1)
  - Abortion counseling pamphlets/resources, 1982-2012 (Box 1)
  - Abortion scholarship, 2012-2013; undated (Box 1)
  - Workshop materials, n 1980; 1985; 1988; circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - Workshop materials, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Job Performance Evaluation, 1976-2005 (Box 5)
  - Herstory of Abortion Counseling at Hope Clinic for Women, 1976-2012 (Box 5)
  - Secondary Literature and Legal Testimony Concerning the Illinois Parental Notice of Abortion Act of 1995, 1983-2013 (Box 5)
  - Abortion and Options Counseling Correspondence, 1994-2000 (Box 5)
  - The Kidnapping of Dr. Hector Zevallos and his wife Rosalie Jean Zevallos, 1982-1984 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1989-2001 (Box 5)
  - Sweatshirts and T-shirt, 1982-2009 (Box 6)
  - Buttons, Mug and Plastic Fetus Figurine, 1989-1994 (Box 7)
- Personal, 1978-2014
  - Autobiography, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1990; 2002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence -Email printouts, 2002-2012 (Box 1)
  - Resume and Writings, 1982; 1986; 2008; 2011 (Box 1)
  - Personal materials, 1978-2014 (Box 1)
  - Turn of the Century Reflection, 1999 (Box 1)
- Publications, 1979-1988
  - Pamphlet - Abortion Legislation in Canada: Reflections, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Hope News issues, 1980; 1981; 1985 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper/Magazine articles concerning abortion, 1979; 1983; undated (Box 1)
  - Original newspaper clippings of Dr. Zevallo's kidnapping, 1982 (Box 2)
- Books, Pamphlets, and Thesis, 1988-2000s
  - Anne Baker's Masters Thesis: Post-Abortion Emotions and How Women Cope, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Abortion and Options Counseling, book by Anne Baker, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Personhood, the Bible and the Abortion Debate, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Herbal Abortion: the Fruit of the Tree of Knowledge, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Mandatory Motherhood: the True Meaning of "Right to Life", 1974 (Box 3)
  - Margaret Sanger: Pioneer of Birth Control, 1969 (Box 3)
  - A Clinician's Guide to Medical and Surgical Abortion, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Post-Abortion Emotions and How Women Cope, Thesis by Anne Baker (Book), 1988 (Box 3)
  - Dispatches from the Abortion Wars by Carole Joffe, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Abortion in the Seventies edited by Warren M. Hern and Bonnie Andrikopoulos, 1977 (Box 3)
  - A Question of Choice by Sarah Weddington, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence accompanying texts, 1990s-2000s (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual, 1985-2010
  - Options No Single Answer: Effective Pregnancy Options Counseling, 1993; 1 VHS cassettes 1 VHS tape in original case. (Box 4)
  - Hope Clinic Inservice Fr. Fly (copy) & Religious pt., 1985; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 4)
  - Fr. Fly & Religious Pt. 2, 2000; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 4)
  - Baptist Rev. Paul Duke (Long Version), 1993; 1 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - "Faith Aloud" and Anne Baker Interview- my story/Uncut Rev. Rebecca Turner, 2010; 1 DVDs 1 DVD with corresponding event program. (Box 4)
  - When Abortion was Illegal: Untold Stories, 1992; 1 VHS cassettes (Box 4)